[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gavin Henry and
today my guest is Jose valim J valim is
the creator of The Elixir programming
language and I love this title a chief
adoption officer at Dash bit a company
that focuses on sustainable open source
and continuous adoption to boost the
Elixir ecosystem he's also a seasoned
speaker and author of three programming
books and an active member of the open
source Community Jose welcome to
software engineering radio is there
anything I missed that you'd like to add
no I think that was a good intro and
thanks for having me thank you perfect
we're going to have a chat about what
Elixir looks like today the challenges
you face at the time you decided to
create Elixir what live book is and
finally Elixir joining the machine
learning world so I like to always ask
you know when we're speaking to someone
that's got major achievements like you
what challenges were you facing at the
time when you thought you know what I'm
going to go and build something versus
I'll try and fix what I'm working with
at the moment what challenges can you
remember you facing when you decided to
create Elixir I'll answer the second
part of the question which is you know
like why I decided to to create
something instead of fixing it and I
hope I'll come back to the first part of
the question but to me like I like to
say that most people when they have a
problem they don't necessarily think
that they will like I'll create a new
programming language that's definitely
going to solve my problems right it's
like the regular expression meme right
like oh I you have a problem use regular
expression and I have two problems and
creating a programming language is
definitely going to bring way more
problems than two so when I started I
was interested in learning I had issues
like writing I was struggling to write
concurrent software in languages like
Ruby and then I say okay if concurrence
this was what 13 years ago 2010 2009 and
then we're we're starting to hear a lot
about concurrency right and today you
have like four cores on your riskwatch
so it's starting to hear a lot about
concurrency and people saying
concurrency is going to be the future so
I was like well if concurrence is going
to be the future I really want to learn
and figure out how I write concurrent
software and then I started on this
journey of learning and thinking I would
learn ideas that I could bring back to
Ruby for example but throughout this
process like I say there are like points
of no return points like there were
things that I learned so when I learn
about functional programming because a
lot of the issues I had with Ruby at the
time that for example if you had two
threads and they were trying to change
the same place in memory that place
would get corrupted and in functional
programming we are not like changing
things in place we are always
transforming them and that really
resonated with me because I thought well
that's a better programming model like
because I don't have to track how things
change over time and it also solves the
concurrency issues so it was a point
where I was like okay I think in the
future when I write software I want to
write software that is uh functional or
if not functional where things are
mostly immutable by default where I am
transforming things I don't want to
motate things anymore I definitely want
to motate things but not as my the full
way of Building Systems yeah and then
the other point was where I learned
about the airling virtual machine and
then I was like well you know this is at
the time so going back to 2010 if you
look at all the programming languages
that were coming out at the time they're
all talking about concurrency they like
go had to focus on concurrency
Swift came later had a focus on
concurrency closure had a focus on
concurrency so concurrency was certainly
a big topic and the thing about theing
virtual machine was not only that they
did concurrency but they did it like
three decades ago and they also solve
The Next Step which is if you're writing
a system where an a machine is not
enough to power that system you need to
use multiple machines the next steps
that you need to think about
distribution and how all those machines
they are going to work together to
tackle a certain problem and then I was
like wellow the viral machine not only
solved the concurrency but they solved
the next problem which is distribution
and I fell completely in love with it
and I was like this is what I want to
use so at some point in this I just want
to learn just by learning I I completely
changed my career in the sense that I
was like this is the software that I
want to write this is how I want to
write it and the more I use the Arling v
machine I fought that there were new
ideas that could be explored and I
thought that the the most productive way
to start this conversation of like how
can we expose or use the earing viral
machine in different ways was by
creating a new programming language and
that led us to where we are wow I mean I
suppose it's it's a great way to follow
something that you get excited about I
was reading an article by Paul gram the
other day which he just released called
do great work and I think the main
takeaway theme from that is you know
follow what's exciting you because
that's going to keep you driven and keep
you interested yeah and I think it ties
in with with the challenges question
because definitely I had a lot of
challenges but I think because of like I
was excited about it I never really saw
that as like a a challenge challenge in
a way you know like you can consider
Challenge in a way that it can even be
crippling or something that would be too
hard to overcome I always saw it it's
like I'm excited about this and there is
work to be done there is always work to
be done so let's do the work and you
know in a step after the the next step
we will eventually get somewhere and I
always had this idea that you know it
could not work at all right so I was not
necessarily too worried about failing I
always had the con like well it can fail
I can spend like three years of my life
and working on this and it's not going
to go anywhere
and I always had in my mind that that's
fine it's not a problem I'll definitely
have learned at T I would have enjoyed
the whole process so that's fine yeah
you always learn something could you
just take a step back and Define the her
Lang Beam for us oh so theing virtual
machine is well the same way that we
have the Java virtual machine and the
Java programming language we have the
Arling virtu machine and the Arling
programming language and the Arling
virtu machine and the program language
they were created by ericon which is a
telecommunication company and they
created with the specific goal of to
power their telecommunication system so
today we say I hear like different
percentages but you know we hear like oh
like the majority like more than
66% of the whole 4G traffic in Europe is
going through Airline machines I hear
people say like 66% of the the global
traffic and things like that but the
point is airlink plays a very big role
in telecommunication today and as I was
saying like to build those systems they
had to tackle a bunch of different
problems related to concurrency
distribution fa tolerance and that's one
of the other things that made me fall in
love with it because you know like many
of the design decisions behind Airline
and the language they were all driven
from like an engineering principle it's
like well we have this problem and how
you're going to solve this problem right
like they did not say look we want
airling to be functional for example
right they did not start with like with
the features and then they derived the
language from it they're like well we
have those problems oh we need
concurrency we need this idea of
supervisors for fault tolerance and they
were building everything from those
principles so one of the reason why
immutability is important from the point
of view of earling is because so if you
have concurrency if you have many things
running at the same time and if now
those different entities they share
State because you have something that is
mutable it's shared if one of those
entities crash right can you guarantee
that when it crash it did not crashed in
a way that the state was corrupted and
there other things that depend on that
same state are now corrupted too or
they'll now be depending on this mutable
shared thing that can break the system
so they're like like well we we don't
want to share a state because if every
guarantee that everything is isolated
it's easier to restart things and
therefore it's easier to have a A system
that can heal itself and be F tolerant
so you know when you are starting
airling and its wisdoms like there are a
lot of you know interesting design
decisions and and why they were done
which is why I I really enjoy working
with it I've never actually made the
connection between IM mutable State and
the supervisors or you know C early and
often because it doesn't matter if you
crash because the data has not been
changed I've just kind of realized that
that's a really good point since you are
I just love saying this the chief
adoption officer if I was to chat to
someone new to Elixir or yourself we
chatting to someone new what would be
the top three things you recommend that
I tell them to make them want to get
excited and jump in like your elevator
pitch as it were that's something that I
am currently rethinking and I guess
we're going to jump into it so for years
like literally I think since 2014 or
2015 so eight potentially nine years I
had like this go-to talk about why
Elixir which is called idioms for
building distributed fa tolerant
applications if you Google that you're
going to find uh versions of the stock
you'll be able to see how I aged through
time because I given it so many times
every time I go to unnown alexir event
that's the talk I give and the talk is
mostly you know like the the elevator
pitch is mostly well it's the v machine
right like it's the problems about
concurrency that we face today how to
write you know maintainable software and
and now I am working on a new talk where
live book is going to be the core of the
talk and use that as a driving point to
show everything that you can do with
Elixir because one of the things that I
think like my previous talk it always
resonated well with maybe it's a
consequence of the events I I was
usually invited to but it always
resonated well with senior developers
right so it's like well you know like
this idea of thinking about concurrency
how you can speed up your tools how you
can reason about failures like sometimes
it's going to make sense once you have
like the let's say the battle cars right
like after you have spent like hours of
your night not sleeping but trying to
understand why a system is failing so I
think like that talk like can resonate
really well after you you have some
experience and you went through some of
the pains and you want to rethink how
you you design and approach systems but
now that we are like with Elixir you
know with live book now we have really a
great platform for to start exploring
and think with ideas and we are starting
to have like visual tools as well that
are really accessible like you know you
are in your live book that resonates
completely with my journey CU I'm senior
as well and all the pain points are
solved in the way that you just
described you know how you can run code
Snippets from the documentation you can
jump onto the I ex interactive thing to
just run your own code or connect to a
live deployment of Elixir and connect to
the beam and run the same functions that
connect to the same database all these
things that you tried to figure out
before when you're younger and solve all
problems it's just I think it's not luck
but it's all just come together at the
right time when everything's kicking off
on that type of ecosystem anyway when
people see lightbook if they haven't as
well that is just mind-blowing as well
so let's move on to lightbook so what is
live book so livebook is a computational
notebook platform and that's a fence way
of saying well think if you have like
your
IDE and a web browser
and like a interactive shell all
integrated into a single place so you
have places where you can write some
code and then you can execute it
immediately we call those places cells
so we can execute a code cell
immediately get the result but because
it's running the browser you can
actually get your alexir code like
plotting a chart or playing some audio
and doing all kinds of interesting
things we're going to to explore and at
the same time you can write like some
pros some text some markdown
documentation so it's this idea of cod
documentation and a reach environment
all in one place and that opens up like
a lot of possibilities of things that
you can do build and explore that's it
in on that show and is that different
from something like code pen or one of
these places where you could run or like
the go for playground for go where you
can run specific code it's much more
than that isn't it yeah so for those who
are familiar with Jupiter notebooks it's
something you know it's closer to
Jupiter notebooks but it's not only a
playground because the playground it's
you think like well it's a single place
right and then I change I evaluate I get
the result but you're not really writing
a document you're not really writing a
story a tutorial an application it's
meant to be like a a scratch Pad it's
something that you're going to throw out
but with live book it's not necessarily
for of course you can explore ideas and
discard them but we use that for
documentation writing applications and
building things that are meant to be
long lived and it's a standalone
application that you can either connect
to on lifebook dodev or run it yourself
on your own desktop or through Docker or
deploy it like a normal web app is s
right yeah exactly it's a web app it's
implemented as a web app but we know we
have like live boot desktop so you just
run that we package that and you can run
that in your machine but at the end of
the day it's a web app it's open source
so as any other web app there are many
different things you could do with it
cool why was it created well so the
story of why why it was created it's
related to machine learning so I'll try
to make it very short but we started as
a fork for machine learning and we can
talk about why we started that and
because Jupiter notebooks and the
biggest eism for machine learning is the
PIP community and we know that you know
Jupiter notebooks they play a very
important role in the machine Learning
Community for python so at the beginning
it was really like well you know what if
we want to do machine learning in Elixir
and Jupiter is important what if we have
like the equivalent of Jupiter for
Elixir so we thought that you know as
part of a machine Learning Journey I was
like well this is going to be a required
stop so we have to tackle it and one of
the things that we could do is that so
in Jupiter which comes from python you
can actually plug different languages I
was like from the beginning say I wanted
to roll our own and that's for two
reasons so one of the reasons is that
alixir is good for web for writing web
applications and a couple years ago we
announced like live view which is a way
of building like Rich interactive
applications without necessarily having
to write JavaScript but it's all
interactive and reactive and you can
build like really modern fence
applications parted by Elixir and I was
like well we have the tooling right to
build this this is what Elixir is in my
view is part of the Phoenix web
framework project that is written Alexa
isn't it yes correct so I was like we we
have the tooling and if you look like at
how people are trying to improve Jupiter
notebook so there are a bunch of like
commercial versions of Jupiter and so on
and they're trying to add features like
collaboration so for example
collaboration something that is very
easy to do with Phoenix right because it
was designed with this realtime
interactive aspect in mind and they was
like okay like that's a problem they
current have and it's a problem that we
can solve and then the other thing was
that one of the main issues that people
have with Jupiter notebooks is that
they're not easy to reproduce and
there's a whole other conversation that
we can have on this but in a n shell
it's like if you have imagine that in
one cell so imagine you have in one
place say x equals one and then the next
cell like the next code that are going
to evolve is like X is equal x + 1 in a
Jupiter notebook it means every time you
execute the second cell the value of x
is going to increment because the way
that Jupiter notebooks work is that
you're working against like this state
that is alongside the notebook and the
problem with that is that imagine that
you create a recipe right and you send
somebody if somebody executes it from
top to bottom you're you're going to be
like xals 1 and x equal x + 1 right so
and then you can say oh the result at
the end was true but if you give it
somebody else and they decided to
execute the last cell two times x is
going to be three so it means that every
time somebody executes that notebook
they may get a different result and then
we're thinking well you know this is
because of mutability alexir is
immutable like he's immutable by default
so we should not have those problems and
if we do not have those problems we can
reink how are going to approach The
Notebook so this is something I think
you know telling the story now it's
something like it's a very different
compared to Elixir because with Elixir I
was like I want to explore I want to
learn I don't necessarily want to to
create something new and with live book
from the very beginning it was clear
that it was worth to create something
new because the difference are so much
that are so many that it's worth
exploring that new Direction and it's
like we're going to get a new tree and
once we shake it a bunch of interesting
things are going to to fall off and we
were excited about exploring that so
that's kind of how we start with life
book and at the beginning like I would
not be able to describe like 20% of the
features that life book has today but
that was the idea right we knew like
like if we plant this seed is like
interesting things are going to happen
and we decided to do it just
to revisit the mutability thing there
because X was assigned a value at the
start of your recipe you would need to
take that and assign it to a new value
to change it cuz X will always be the
same that's the point there isn't it so
yes and no so in Elixir that's something
that it often can be confusing in Elixir
the values they are immutable so if you
think of a value it's something that is
in memory and the thing that is in
memory is immutable but the values you
can change to where the variable is
going to point true so in Elixir I can
say
list is equal a list with 1 two three
and then I can say list is equal
456 I'm just changing to where the
variable points and this is a is a
transformation that only happens in the
program but when it comes to the memory
nothing's being changed or manipulated
in memory so the difference between
Python and elixir here is that python
when you change X it changes every time
change X you can think like each cell it
gets the all day state in the notebook
and then it changes these things and it
dumps somewhere so every time you do X+
one it goes to this Global place to say
hey what is the value of x and then say
Oh it's true let's increment one it's
three and it puts again back in This
Global place where in Elixir everything
is linear so if the value of x before
you execute a piece of code was one at
the end the value can be two to but if
you execute that piece of code again we
don't get the value from Like This
Global pce place that is shared we just
go back to the value of x before the
cell so it's like a mathematical formula
right so we have the inputs we have the
outputs and in this case the input to a
cell is not going to change unless you
change things before the cell I don't
know if I can explain if it makes sense
yeah no that's perfect because that
reinforces the view of when you're
debugging IM code you know you don't
have to try and figure out what that
value changed to cuz it's not going to
change and I think like that's it's a
good example right which is like if you
are the bugging code if it was immutable
so imagine that you have xal 1 and xal
X+ one if you put a debugging between
those two lines in Elixir the value of x
is always going to be one right because
even if you change the value of x later
is not going to affect the value of x
before right and I think that's the
difference right it's very linear yeah I
think in some of the examples in books
and documentation that's when they
usually introduce recursion so they can
show you how to increment a variable by
returning a different value each time is
that right so in Elixir when we use
recursion is well there are many reasons
why we use recursion so one of the ways
that you you can think about it is we
have the daa structures and in order to
Traverse those daa structures you can
use recursions but but when it comes to
a state so if you think like well in
Elixir if nothing is I don't know if I
can explain this for audio but if
nothing is mutable if everything is
immutable right like how do you create
state so imagine that somewhere in your
web application you want to store how
many users are connected at the same
time right so that thing needs to be
needs to be something needs to be shared
State because every time some more joins
You Need to Say Hey I want to increment
this by one every time somebody leaves
you want to decrement and you want to be
able to increment or decrement this from
anywhere you want right so it needs to
be state it needs to be shared somehow
in Elixir the way you would achieve this
is using recursion so we create this
idea of this thing like called processes
and those processes they can send and
receive messages so what they do is that
they have so a counter would work
something like this you have a function
that you call it saying we have a
function called Loop and then you start
with a value of zero Loop is zero which
is your current counter and then you're
going to receive messages if you receive
the message of increment you're going to
call the same function you're going to
call the same Loop function but
incrementing they state by one and if
you receive a message of decrement
you're going to decrement one from the
state and you can receive a get message
which is and then when you receive a get
message you are going to send a message
back to the person who who sent you the
message say Hey you wanted to get the
value of the counter here is the value
back so the discussion of recursion when
we are thinking about immutability and
mutability in Elixir is because we use
recursion and message passing as the way
to emulate state right so there is no
mutable State per se we have functions
with their state and then you can send
message and back but again you are never
really mutating the counter right again
it's like never the ax of value is like
it's changing under your feet you're
just pointing to different things as you
move forward
thank you that was a perfect explanation
that helped me as well so hope it helps
the listeners so we'll just finish up
the live book section with two more
questions before we get into machine
learning in general with Elixir so live
book was created because you want to be
able to support machine learning and
alixir and for a way for users data
scientists programmers to to explore
data through lifebook is that correct
yes that's how it
started okay and the this is just a
question from me how does it save the
code you're working on how does that
work and that's also another going back
to the Jupiter conversation so one of
the positive and negative things about
being widely adopted as Jupiter is that
you have plenty of materials and plenty
of experience of people saying hey you
know this should have been done
differently or this needs to improve and
per to get started means we can consume
all this material as well and learn the
lessons that jup learn for time and it's
there documented for us to learn and one
of the things in Jupiter is that so if
you think of a notebook if you think of
a document right you know how it's going
to be shared some things they are opaque
like you know if you have a a Word
document or an Excel document and you
try to open it like in an nitor it's
just going to be like blobs I think Exel
for sure maybe docs depending one of the
formats not but you know it's a blob you
can't do anything with it and that was
one of the things that people like a
Jupiter notebook you know you cannot
open it in disk and this has problems
that like doing a code reval for example
can be hard because you canot just
submit a change and have somebody
reveiew that today there are tools in
GitHub to improve that but it's not
plain text and for us it was we wanted
to tackle this problem so live book
notebooks they say that they are live
markdown files and it's a subset of
markdown we restrict a little bit the
markdown that you have there so it has a
very specific structure and that's it so
you know you can open it up you can
review it on on GitHub drop some
comments and all this kind of stuff oh
excellent so you can see your Elixir
programming in the markdown document
perfect okay we're about halfway through
now so I'm going to move us on to all
the exciting progress in the machine
learning world for Elixir so I've got
another question here which we we're
struggling to do at the moment in your
own words what is machine learning yeah
so one of the ways that I saw like
machine learning and I again I don't
know if it's good but one of the ways
that or if I'm recollecting properly one
of the ways that I saw it described is
machine learning is about defining
models to execute certain tasks that it
would be impossible or very error prone
for us to define or declare those tasks
manually right so for example think
about a Chaz game like sure there are
the rules of Chess and we can describe
but imagine that you want to build a
model that wins a chess game it would be
very hard for us to encode those rules
in software right like using
conditionals or whatever right oh like
you know there are so many states so
many combinations so the idea of machine
learning is how can I define a model
something that I can train that can
learn from based on something some data
some training set and then execute that
ask for us without us explicitly
describing or declaring what we wanted
to do I guess that's one possible
interpretation yeah that's good enough
for me I mean in Sean's book he says
exactly that once you get to a point
where you're doing rules for some type
of system and there's so many edge cases
that you then move to machine learning
and either building a model or finding
the right model and he says the model
I'll put a link to the book for everyone
in this he says a model is just another
name for the algorithm that you choose
to Crunch the data set which is the NX
data structure which we'll get to I
think just to summarize why is elixir a
suitable programming language for
machine learning think we've touched
upon it on past half an hour or so yeah
so interestingly when I started with
Elixir darling machine was not
necessarily a good candidate for machine
learning but if you look at machine
learning in Python for example a lot of
it's powered by libraries in in C C++ I
think some in for train so it's all
Native code and it all so a lot of
people say you know like one of the the
merits in Python for machine learning
it's how python can be such a good glue
language between you know the high level
python software and the low level code
Inc and in the virtual machine because
so there are things we did not talk
about like how so I kind of mentioned
that we write our code that runs inside
those processes that they send and
receive messages and we can kind of
Pierce together that those processes
they are all isolated they don't share
anything right they can only exchange
messages and and they are very cheap
they're very lightweight and we can run
like millions of those at the same time
and the airling uh virtual machine it's
also uh preemptive which means that
those processes there's it's not
possible for one of those processes to
starve the system system to do so much
work that the rest of the system it
cannot respond because that thing is
busy and in order for this to happen
it's essential that you know like if you
have an infinite Loop for example if you
have anything that it's very expensive
it's essential for that thing to if it
has to do a lot of work for it to say
hey I'm going to do some quota of work
and then I'm going to stop and then the
virtual machine will check if anything
else like need needs to do some work and
if something else needs to do work those
other things are going to do the work
and then you come back so you are
preempting like everybody gets some
amount of work and then eventually
everybody is going to get to to the end
of their journey is going to finish the
work that they have to do and the issue
with calling C cold was that well if I
just go and call a c cold that is going
to do like some very expensive 3D or 4D
matrix multiplication that thing could
take a lot of time and that can starve
the rest of the system so almost 10
years ago in order to for you to if you
wanted to integrate with native code in
earling you had to re write the native
code you had to write the native code to
say look I'm going to do just some
amount of work and then I'm going to
yield back to theirl virtu machine for
it to see if if something else needs to
run and then do a little bit more so it
had to do all this yielding and of
course depending on the like it may be
hard like to rewrite imagine we if we
had to rewrite all the machine learning
like algorithms and computations to work
based on those ideas it would be a lot
of work a lot of time spent so they
introduced about eight nine years ago
this idea called so when you have to
call C cod in earling we say it's a
native implemented function we call it
nif so it's native code lowlevel code
native implemented function and they
introduce this idea of dirty niffs and
the idea of a dirty KN is that you say
if that dirty NE is going to do a bunch
of CPU work or if it's going to do a
bunch of iio work and we have separate
trads that those trads can run and you
customize how many trads you want to
have so you you give separate trads to
run this dirty work but that dirty work
is not going to run together with your
Elixir code so it's running on a
separate operating system tread so they
introduce this whole abstraction of
dirty kns and so basically they added
this way of how we can now integrate
native code in the airline VTO machine
and you know once we had that if you say
if you compare alexir with python it's
like well you know now we can integrate
native code so we can bring those all
those algorithms those libraries for
machine learning that's exactly what we
did so for the machine learning in
Elixir is not like we are starting from
like all the low level from scratch we
are using Google xlaa which is a an
accelerated linear algebra library from
Google which Google uses for tensor flow
it's the same Library we just we wrote
bindings we wrote bindings for that and
we build on top of that we also have
bindings for de torch which is what the
py torch library from Facebook right
another big player of machine learning
it's binding to the lowlevel library
that the py Tor uses as well so that's
how we started with the machine learning
and it was mostly like well you know
technically we can do it and it was we
talk about show more it and his
excellent machine learning book and
before he wrote The Machine learning
book he wrote a genetic algorithms in
Elixir book I say like this is the book
that changed my life but I never read it
and the reason I say that is because as
soon as that book was published I think
on the first or the day after I sent an
email to Sean I was like this is very
exciting I was always interested on
having more machine learning stuff in
Elixir let's build something together
and that's when we got oh we can build
something together oh we can use the
same native libraries that python uses
and we started slowly building this
whole infrastructure that wasn't out
very long ago was it 2021 he published
that book I'll put it in the show notes
as well i' actually got it it's a good
one okay so that was a lovely
description and history lesson how you
got to the point of Elixir being
suitable so as I understand it and I'm
hope you're going explain there's five
elements to the machine learning Elixir
ecosystem and that would be NX skolar
Explorer Axion and Bumblebee could you
take us through that or you know confirm
IOD understand that correctly yeah yeah
perfect so I think there are two
building blocks one it's
anx and NX stands for numerical Elixir
and what it does is that the main
abstraction is there is something that
we call a tensor so a answer is a
multi-dimensional data structure as
programmers we are familiar with lists
or vectors and those are one dimensional
right you're also familiar with matrices
right which are 2D right so you have two
dimensions in there and then so a tensor
can represent things that are one
dimension they are two dimensional they
can also represent things that are three
or four dimension so for example
something that is three-dimensional for
our computer it's an image because you
have the height you have the width and
then images they have like the RGB
layers right the red green and blue
layers each of them get like a bite to
represent depending on the image format
right but they get a bite to represent
how much red is there how much green is
there how much blue is there you have
some other images which are like
rgba but yeah so you have three
dimensions right you have width you have
height and then you have another
dimension which is to have like the
channels right RGB or rgba and so on so
that's three dimensional a video is
going to have another dimensional that
because you can think of a video so it's
going to be 40 because you can have can
think of a video to be a batch of images
right so tensors allow us to represent
that right to represent all those things
and depending what you want to do so
even if you're thinking simply about it
like well if I have an image how do you
rotate an image right or how do I rotate
a video how do I convert a video to
black and white right if you think about
all those things we can express those as
Transformations on top of the sensor and
NX provides a bunch of lowlevel
Primitives not really low level binding
to low level Primitives to do this
operation right to do all those things
so we can multiply matrices we can
invert we can add layers remove layers
there are a bunch of things that you can
do and NX does it NX does a lot more so
if somebody's listening to this episode
they're coming from Python and X can
also we have this idea of like serving
tensors we have idea of numerical
definitions we talk all about that in
the project R mey but in that's what the
anex does it defines those tensors so
that's the lowest level yes that's
almost everything Builds on top of that
so for example one of the things that
build on top of that is a project called
scholar so now when we talk about
machine learning a lot of people they
think about neuron networks right or
deep learning that's what people are
thinking about so we have a library for
that called AEL but we also have a
library called scholar which is more
about the traditional machine learning
and now we have like algorithms like for
example clustering like imagine you have
some data right and you can distribute
this data in a space and you can say hey
can I break this data into cluster find
things that are related to each other or
imagine that you have some points you
want to do like you want to find a
polinomial curve that is going to fit
those points as close as possible or you
can do a linear regression so his Coler
is a traditional machine in library
that's what it has in there and it's
built on top of NX and the other cool
thing about NX is that all the code that
you write you can run it either all the
code can be compiled just in time to run
on your CPU and that's can make it like
much much faster or if you have a GPU
you can also compile that code to run on
the GPU as well so everything that I'm
saying about scholar it means that it
can run on the CPU or on the GPU as well
and then a
is also about machine learning but it's
about deep learning in particular so
it's about the abstractions for building
neur networks so neuron networks we
break them into they have a bunch of
layers each layer has like different
capabilities it adds different features
so you need a whole library to define
those layers if you want to train a
neuron Network you need to figure out
how you're going to train the neuron
Network as well and axel is a library
that takes care of that so it's the
building blocks for building a neuron
network if you think about a neuron
network has a bunch of layers stacked on
top of each other Aon is going to define
those layers and all you have to do is
to connect those layers together and
that's going to give us deep learning
and new networks in Elixir and it's
built again on top of anx and then
bumblebee comes on top of that and what
bumblebee has that well we have a bunch
of predefined existing NE networks today
right and some they are like very
popular right like some archit we often
call them architectures so like GPT is
very familiar because of cat GPT we have
stable diffusion we have whisper which
is for speech to text there are a bunch
of existing architectures existing neon
networks and often what people do is
that because the most expensive thing is
training a NE Network it needs a really
large amount of data and sometimes
people they spend like hundreds of
thousands of dollars to train your
network
and there are people who train those
neuron networks and they make the result
of the training which we call our the
model weights they make it open source
they make it available maybe not open
source the best way to describe it but
it's available and you can download it
and you can use it so for example well
maybe it's a good time to say this so if
you are excited about trying those
things out you can install live book in
your machine we have this thing called
smart cells that we can go back and talk
about them but you start a new notebook
you click on the smart cell button and
you say hey I want to have a new network
you click that button as well say I want
to speech to text new network and it's
going to configure the new network for
you so you can start running a speech to
text your network with elixir on your
computer and give it a try and again
this happens because we have implemented
those models in Elixir and because
somebody trained his new network made
the model weights available and we
download it to our machine and now you
can run that thing and I can say hello
darkness my old friend and is going to
give me the text back hello darkness my
old friend and everything else and this
part where we build existing models and
we can download the weights of the model
to your machine so you can run it that's
the Bumblebee project right and that's
built on top of axon so to sum up so far
we have an X which is the building block
and then we have a scholar which is all
about traditional machine learning and
then we have axon which is about deep
learning about NE Networks and
bumblebees gets the framework right so
if you're coming from web you can think
like you know get Phoenix or raos or in
Jungle right like imagine that you have
a web framework that's going to be aent
but imagine that we had a bunch of like
ready web applications all developed for
you for you to try out and run them and
that would be bumblebee it's basically a
bunch of existing models that you can
they already work they have the
parameters you can just get them try out
deploy to production and start running
them those cover four of these I'm going
to use this opportunity to to have a
break before I go forward I'm going to
go through an example and pull apart and
summarize everything we've just talked
about because there was a lot of new
terms there so NX is the fundamental
different types of data structures that
we need to get the data we're analyzing
into into some type of format that fits
NX so that's the bottom layer
scholar is our traditional machine
learning so I would understand that to
be you need to know what you're looking
for whether it's polom or linear or the
other terms you said so you need to know
what you're looking for in order to use
that a on you nicely explained is the
framework that you're using which brings
you into neural networks or deep
learning which will need to take a step
back and to find the difference between
or the complimentary parts of machine
learning and neural network
and then bumblebee is kind of the nice
go and grab this existing model or
algorithm from somewhere like hugging
bear that host these types of things
download it and apply that to our data
set or the data we're interested in is
that about right yeah just with the
correction hugging face hugging face I
put hugging bear in here yeah yeah no it
would also be a great name hugging bear
but yeah it's hugging face and for those
who are not familiar they I like to say
I don't know if they like the
description but I like to say it's like
like it's the GitHub for machine
learning and for AI and neur network so
all the models are there with the
parameters and you can deploy and run
and give things a try I really enjoy
everything that they have been
contributing to the machine learning
ecosystem and and your on network is
that a bunch of computers or how do we
Define that so it doesn't have to be a
bunch of computers so a neuron Network
you know it's a model and I think I'm
not sure exactly how I would say what
exactly is a neuron network but it's a
machine learning model and I think if it
has like some specific layers that would
describe them as a neural network but I
I'm not sure like what is the essential
bit of everything that a neural network
has that makes it a neural network like
so for example in scholar we have models
why those things they are not NE Network
I'm not 100% sure what is the thing that
makes it different okay I get the
feeling that's going to be another show
it's going into deep learning and um
neural networks yeah Sean would
definitely be ready to answer yeah I
think we could do a deep on that there
is one I think just as a parenthesis
here I think one of the cool things
about the neuron networks is that you
define the layers that compose of the
neuron Network and it uses because a
neuron network has two parts right we
say it's the training part where you
have to train the new Network and I said
that it's expensive and there's the
inference parts that after it's trained
you say hey convert this pitch to text
or tell me if there is a dog or a horse
in this picture right that's the
inference thing and again I don't know
if this is what makes a new network in
your network but one of the interesting
things is that the training the code is
derived from how you stack the layers
together you don't have to say here's
how I train it you just assemble the
layers together and then we use
mathematical properties to derive how we
are going to train the neuron Network
and maybe that's what makes a neuron
Network an actual neuron network but I'm
not sure okay that's cool we did a show
actually in February episode 249 with
William Falcon on optimizing deep
learning models and that goes in depth
into pie torch and P torch lightning and
things things that you mentioned so
reference that for the
listeners okay let's try if we can in
the last 10 minutes or so
to come up with an example that uses
everything so my interest at the moment
is fraud detection whether that is in
telecom's world or you know API abuse or
a bank transaction that's
fraud would you be able to take us
through if possible where you start with
that you know you've got a bunch of API
logs or events or call data records or
phone calls that would be your raw data
that You' kind of got to to find a model
for get into shape how does all that
work I have no
idea good answer yeah as I said like I
am working on an A and sometimes Sean is
like hey this new network is slow or it
doesn't compile I don't know what it
does I don't understand it but it gives
me a way to to reproduce it like that I
can run it on my machine I don't
actually need to care about what it does
and how it stitched together I can go
there and I can optimize it I can figure
out ways of making you know it efficient
and improve it and even help come up
with the abstractions but when it comes
to using them for using them to solve
the problems I I don't know what about
Bumblebee when we go and get a model
what are we actually running that
against or on your data what do you mean
when you're downloading this model that
fits your use case
are you inputting like a bunch of CSV
records or you know when you're using
Life Book yeah so going back to the
ecosystem right you said there were five
and there is one that I did not cover
which is Explorer that's right yeah yeah
that's the fifth one so everything we
have talking about an X bumblebee
axon scholar those things when we think
about tensors they are all zeros and
ones they can only represent numbers in
them right and so like it doesn't really
know about words right so you may say
okay so how can I do like spam detection
or or how can I do speech to text if the
thing doesn't know about words and so
for example we have something before
which is called like a tokenizer and
what it does is that it goes through the
text for example you also have to train
but it goes through the text and say Hey
you know this token here is going to get
the number one this other token here so
get like hello it says like the hell
thing maybe or ha is going to get the
number one low gets the number two and
you split everything in tokens SPAC is a
token and you give the numbers right but
that's not all like that's not all the
data that we have that's only strings we
also have dat times right which maybe we
can treat them as a numbers but maybe
they encode different properties in
there that can be interesting like maybe
the interesting thing of a date time is
not really the date part but the time
depending on what you to do right so for
example maybe for all detection is more
common at midnight right so it doesn't
matter the date it matters that that
it's midnight right so data is richer
right it's not only zeros and ones and
we need to be able to get this data from
aess v file from your database somewhere
you need to be able to get this data and
to message it right to transform it So
eventually we can transform it enough
that it becomes zeros and ones in a way
that we can feed into those tensors
right so that's what the Explorer
project does right so if you're are
thinking about so let's try to put
everything together so Explorer is you
can think about it as an Exel or as a
table a database table right it's
columns that have a type and a bunch of
rows and you want to process those
columns in a very efficient way as fast
as you can right because a lot of the
issues with machine learning it's about
like massaging the data so if you're
using live book your workflow would be
something like well you know I'm going
to open up live book I'm going to bring
the CSV into live book and I'm going to
use Explorer to part that CSV into a
meaningful data structure and then from
there a data engineer or data scientist
is going to try to explore a little bit
the data try to understand some parts
maybe the data is dirty maybe know like
sometimes the numbers are less the the
names maybe the name is important
sometimes the names are last name comma
first name sometimes first name last
name maybe the dates they're not
necessarily correct sometimes with time
zone sometimes with VA you may wanted to
do a lot of messaging on that data and
then eventually after you message that
data it's in a state it's good maybe
there's an existing machine learning
model that you can try and that existing
machine learning model would be trained
on data of some sort say look the person
who trained that machine learning model
massage the data in this way and then
you massage the same way give it to the
machine learning model the machine
learning model is going to tell you if
it's fraud or not or maybe you need to
get an existing model you have to train
it and then if you have to train you get
all your data for example so you need
somebody to go through this data and say
hey this was fraud this was not frud you
need to label the data and then you
define this data that you're going to
use to train and test the model and then
there are a bunch of techniques of
things that you can do here but then
what you do is that if you know what is
fraud what is not you use that to train
the model you use that to test the model
to see if the model is accurate because
you may not want to have false negatives
or false positives and after you go
through this whole process several tries
most likely the hope is that you're
going to arrive to A model they're going
to be happy to run in production and our
tools are going to help with that part
as well and give a bunch of options on
how you want to deploy those models how
you want to scale it in the same machine
different machines one GPU multiple gpus
and so on that's kind of the general
overview of the problem I'm trying not
to laugh here because for someone that
just said they had no idea that was a
perfect explanation of how it all works
cuz that's how I had it in my head and
you explained it perfectly so thank you
so just to summarize you Explorer pulls
apart the date you're interested
depending on your business logic and
your skill set as a data scientist or
whatever you're trying to pull apart
what's important from that data to you
and Y and then you get it into the shape
and form to either run against existing
models or create your own which ends up
in NX in a GPU or CPU yeah you asked me
to paint monaa and what I said is that
it has a mouth eyes I news yeah that's
that's the rest is up to you do you have
any idea of how you build a model versus
an off-the-shelf one from hugging face
is that something this can help you with
the machine learning ecosystem in Elixir
yeah so usually you build a model you
would get axon which has the layers and
the models they would say oh you know
like for image recognition is going to
be something oh you're going to have a
dense layer and then you have like a
convolution layer and then you would
stack the layers together that's part
one of like defining a model will be
like sticking those layers together
right but then you have to train it
right right which is the tricky part and
that's going to give you the model
weights that you would be able to to run
in production as well one of the things
that is also worth saying for people are
not familiar with machine learning is
that you can also like f tune so for
example you can get like a general model
for like fraud detection but then it may
not be like super accurate on your data
but it may be more if efficient both in
terms of costs or even more accurate for
you to get instead of training
everything from from scratch for you to
tune that model on your data so you
don't need as much data as before if
you're just going to fine-tune something
that exists and that's also an option
but yeah like I assume like most people
they're not
necessarily so let me try to recap so
it's like it's three parts right so one
part is like what layers do you have and
how you're going to stack those layers
together that's one part of the problem
which is basically done by research like
researchers around the world they are
like working on those things thinking
about new layers and how to stack them
but after somebody publishes a paper
like how to do image recognition how to
do FR detection right they say how the
layers should be stacked together and
you use axon to stack those layers
together right and then somebody has to
train to get the parameters and do the
labeling yeah labeling is part of the
training data and then after you have
all those things you can give it an
input like some data that you got from
CSV or some text if you're doing spam
detection so you're going to have your
input and you're going to have your
output which can also be different kinds
right it can be a boo thing oh this is a
spam do not a Spam but if you're doing
image recognition or image
classification right it's a dog it's a
cat you know you may have all different
kinds of things that it's going to say
and the interesting thing is that it
doesn't necessarily say it's a dog or a
cat for example or a horse or a hot dog
right it just says well I am like 60%
sure it's a dog you know 10% sure it's a
cat like 1% sure it's a hot dog right
and it just gives you the percentage
it's going to be one of those and then
you have to decide if that's good enough
right or if it's ambiguous and you don't
want to make a decision and so on I
suppose that would be like your example
before where if it's a poorly trained
model you might show a picture of a of a
lady and it says yeah I'm 60% sure this
is the monaa but as you fine tune it and
say you need to be looking for this this
this it would it would find it yeah that
could be one of the things so again my
understanding I'm not 100% sure is that
so for example imagine that you want to
you have very specific use like you want
to identify different breads of dog or
imagine that you work with tooling like
very specific tooling where you know
like maybe where you're working for us
we you see like three different kinds of
hammer and we say it's a hammer right
but depending on what you're working
like no this is a hammer with the square
hat that I use for this this a HW for
this and this right some people may have
like specific uses you get an existing
model that already does the image
recognition and then you find tun it to
teach you about like the specializations
that's one way to go about yeah I think
that's called assisted learning isn't it
I'm not sure because there are like so
many terms related to that I've heard
like transfer learning I know there's
fine-tuning I know there's like the
reinforcement learning which is
something else
but there are so many terms that I'm not
exactly sure what makes one or the other
like what are the differences between
them it reminds me of when spam assassin
first came out and as a system
administrator I used to spend tons of
time dumping folders of spam into spam
assassin and training it again you know
you have to constantly keep feeding the
new changes okay I think that's us
pretty much at the end of the show yeah
just one thing because I thought that
came because you mentioned spam it's I
think it's worth like also mentioning
that the spam filters they got like
really popular before like deep learning
became a thing right which I think
points back to a scholar right like the
way that people were doing spam
filtering I believe before deep learning
is that they were using tools like
scholar they were using traditional
machine learning tools and one of the
advantages of that is that usually they
are much cheaper to run they don't requ
ire that many resources so it's
something that depending on what you're
doing you know like maybe you should
consider oh traditional machine learning
is fine I don't need the Deep learning
one and it's something worth thinking
about yeah thank you so what's next for
you in the machine learning world what
are you currently staying up late doing
or you know looking forward to doing in
the morning yeah so this is something
that I want to announce I want to
publish within the next month I think
like for when we started this machine
learning stuff which was about three
years and a half ago like I had a huge
list of things to do like really massive
list of things to do and learn and
explore because you are at that point in
your journey that you need to know what
to do and what not to do like you say
like look it's not worth investing time
in this particular area this is where we
should focus on and like I had a huge
list and we are at a point where like we
still have a lot of work to do of course
but the the core it of the things in the
list it's all tackled so now we are we
will continue to focus on like improving
what is there adding new
capabilities rather than you know like
adding a new Foundation like a block
like we said like five blocks they're
not necessarily thinking about the six
or the seventh block the blocks they're
in place and now it's about continue to
improve them and that's pretty much our
plan with just continue improving adding
more features to anx or to bumblebee
implementing more models and as
companies and teams that are starting to
run those things in production I'm sure
we're going to get more and more
feedback that we are going to take and
continue to improve in the tooling so
I'm really excited and proud that we are
getting out of this like discover Loop
and now getting into like the cycle
where we continue improving rather than
starting New Foundation all the time
thank you I think we did a great job of
covering why anyone should invest time
in The Elixir world for their next
machine learning project but if there
was one thing you'd like a software
engineer to remember from our show what
would you like it to be yeah know that's
a good question I'll have to think about
it uh was there anything that we missed
I forgot to mention I think through the
description hopefully folks got the idea
of all the exciting things that that you
can do with Elixir right like you can as
I was saying you can start live book and
you can start running a machine learning
model and from live book you can kind of
build a chat app where you can send
audio and it's going to convert that to
text you can send an image it's going to
classify that image it's going to
generate text there are all those crazy
things that you can do and have those
things interact with your alixir
codebase in all interesting ways plot
graphs transform data so that's kind of
like
that's where I want to think like you
know what alexir is for for today I'm
thinking like well I want it to be this
tool where you can kind of throw any
problem at it and you're going to have a
great time like tackling that problem
and we are going to have good
abstractions for solving that problem
that's where I hope we are going towards
thanks well for me I'm going to have a
go of what people should remember from
the show and this is how I think of it
Elixir is not just a programming
language it's a whole ecosystem I think
that's where it's got to today over the
past 10 years I think people just think
of it as a programing language but when
you're actually using it daytoday and
you've got the whole tool chain
ecosystem places to reach out
communities to join it's it's not just a
programming language so where can people
contact you or you know reach out to
Chief adoption officer I just love that
where can they reach out to you yeah so
places so if it's something like
regarding let's say I don't want to say
Enterprise but if it's something related
with business company go to dash b.co
our website and you can reach out to me
there we are a very small company that's
why I I didn't want to call like CEO
because I always find it funny when it's
like oh I'm the CEO of like a
three-person
company and I also like I don't want to
call myself a CTO because like we're not
really running any technology like we do
open source right so I thought like oh
Chief adoption officer or I was think
like chap open source officer but that
like doesn't make a lot of sense so I
was like chief chief adoption out but
yeah it can be there but otherwise you
can reach out to me through the alexir
Forum or through GitHub that's where I
am most active well thank you for coming
on the show it's been a real pleasure
this is Gavin Henry for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for having
me thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for listening okay